<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The report of the Committee for receiving informations concerning the Popish plot upon the complaint of Mr. Peter Norris presented to the House of Commons, upon Thursday the 9th day of Decemb. 1680.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons. Committee to Receive Informations Concerning the Popish Plot.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1084A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07951440</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07951440</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57035)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1211:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The report of the Committee for receiving informations concerning the Popish plot upon the complaint of Mr. Peter Norris presented to the House of Commons, upon Thursday the 9th day of Decemb. 1680.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons. Committee to Receive Informations Concerning the Popish Plot.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>p. 123-129.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright and Richard Chiswell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:40664:1"/>
            <p>I Appoint <hi>John Wright,</hi> and <hi>Richard Chiſwel,</hi> to Print this REPORT, Peruſed by me, According to the Order of the HOUSE of COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS; And that no other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon preſume to Print it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. 11th. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Wi WILLIAMS,</hi> Speaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40664:1"/>
            <p>THE REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE, For Receiving INFORMATIONS CONCERNING THE Popiſh Plot; Upon the Complaint of Mr. Peter Norris.</p>
            <p>Preſented to the HOUSE of COMMONS, Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 9th. day of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright,</hi> at the Crown on <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-hill,</hi> and <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb facs="tcp:40664:2"/>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:40664:2"/>
            <head>THE REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE For Receiving INFORMATIONS Concerning the Popiſh Plot, Upon the COMPLAINT of Mr. <hi>Peter Norris,</hi> preſented to the Houſe of COMMONS upon <hi>Thurſday Decemb.</hi> 9. 1680.</head>
            <p>UPon conſideration of the Information given at the Barr by Mr. <hi>Peter Norris</hi> and Referred to this Committee,</p>
            <p>Reſolved by this Committee, that the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of this matter be Reported Specially.</p>
            <p>This Committee in the firſt place, after hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid <hi>Norris</hi> his Complaint, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Papers were taken from him, ſent for the ſaid Papers which were informed then to be in a Cheſt in the <hi>Council Chamber,</hi> which Papers were brought to this Committee by an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory which the ſaid <hi>Norris</hi> then acknowledged to be all, and they ſtill remain with this Committee.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:40664:3"/>
            <p> In the next place, they proceeded to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine upon what occaſion the ſaid <hi>Norris</hi> was ſent beyond Sea <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which not only by the ſaid Papers, but alſo by a Certificate delivered to the Chairman of this Committee from the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and divers other Informations as well as the ſaid <hi>Norris</hi> his Inſtructions given by Dr. <hi>Tonge,</hi> was to fetch over one <hi>Dowdall</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſt, who had been converſant with the Prieſt in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> who managed the Plot both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and mixing himſelf among them, was privy to the whole Plot, which the ſaid <hi>Dowdall</hi> by ſeveral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had made known to Dr. <hi>Tonge</hi> which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were peruſed by the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſatisfaction was given by a known Merchant in <hi>London,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Dowdall</hi> was an honeſt man, of good underſtanding, and might be credited.</p>
            <p>Then the Committee proceeded to inquire, who at any time had knowledge of the ſending over for the ſaid <hi>Dowdall,</hi> and found by an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Council, bearing date the eighteenth day of <hi>July</hi> 1679. that the ſaid <hi>Dowdall</hi> by the name of <hi>Edward Dowdall,</hi> was permitted to come from <hi>Dover</hi> and ſtay for a Month, but in that Order there is no mention of <hi>Dowdall</hi>'s being a Prieſt. And it likewiſe appears to this Committee, that not long after the ſaid Order for his coming over, <hi>Dowdall</hi> dyed, and not without ſuſpicion that it was a Violent Death: but it doth not appear to this Committee, that the Death of <hi>Dowdall</hi> was known in <hi>England</hi> till after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of <hi>Norris,</hi> who was ſent to fetch the ſaid <hi>Dowdall</hi> over, which was about Ten Months
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40664:3"/>after the Date of the ſaid Order of Council.</p>
            <p>Upon which, this Committee proceeded to Examine, how it came to paſs, that the ſaid <hi>Norris</hi> was in ſuch danger beyond Sea; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly at his coming aboard the Pacquett-Boat at <hi>Calais,</hi> and likewiſe his Impriſonment at <hi>Dover</hi> in the Common Priſon, and his being brought from <hi>Dover</hi> by a Meſſenger, and they found the Cauſe of it to be a Deſcription given of <hi>Peter Norris</hi> to Secretary <hi>Jenkins</hi> the Twenty Ninth of <hi>May</hi> 1680. in theſe words, Peter Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, <hi>ſome call him</hi> Morris <hi>a</hi> Scotch-man, <hi>handſome, neat Face, ſanguine Complexion, ſhort Noſe, bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, white Wigg, ſlender Body, little Stature, Civil and Smooth in Diſcourſe, ſpeaking</hi> French; <hi>aged Thirty Four Years more or leſs, Taylor by Trade:</hi> and under this Deſcription, written with another Hand and Ink theſe words <hi>(viz.) Went into</hi> France <hi>on</hi> Wedneſday <hi>was three weeks to bring with him a Prieſt.</hi> Thereupon this Committee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to Examine, who brought this Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to the ſaid Secretary, and where and by whom it was drawn, with all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that they could find about it. And firſt they found, that <hi>Thomas Sheridon</hi> a Gentleman, who affirmed himſelf a Proteſtant born in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> heretofore employed in Collecting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues there, and lately with the Duke at his Court at <hi>Bruſſells,</hi> and came over with him in the ſame Yacht, confeſſed upon his Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he carryed the ſaid Deſcription to the ſaid Secretary; but it being ſhewed him, he denyed the writing any part of it, ſave the laſt Line; but confeſſed that it was written and brought to him by one <hi>Anthony Day</hi> Doctor of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40664:4"/>Phyſick to the Late Army in <hi>Flanders.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſaid <hi>Sheridon</hi> was commanded to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſaid <hi>Day,</hi> and with him to attend.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Day</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sheridon</hi> both appearing were examined ſeverally.</p>
            <p>And firſt the ſaid <hi>Day,</hi> who confeſt himſelf a Papiſt, and pretended very little knowledge of Mr. <hi>Sheridon,</hi> but that coming to give him a viſit, which he had not done of ſix weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Mr. <hi>Sheridon</hi> began to diſcourſe of News, and particularly of the Plot; to which the ſaid Doctor replyed, that now the whole Plot would be diſcovered and laid open; for he heard there was one gone beyond Sea to fetch over a Prieſt that knew of the whole Plot: and doth not remember any thing more at that time but common diſcourſe. But ſome few dayes after meeting with Mr. <hi>Sheridon,</hi> the ſaid Mr. <hi>Sheridon</hi> deſired him to deſcribe the perſon that was ſo ſent over; the ſaid Dr. <hi>Day</hi> replyed, that he knew not the perſon that was gone, nor the Prieſt he was to fetch: but that <hi>John Butler,</hi> keeper of a Brandy-ſhop near the French Embaſſadours upon diſcourſe had told him ſo; to whom Mr. <hi>Sheridon</hi> deſired him to go and get the deſcription, which he did accordingly. And the deſcription being ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, confeſſed he writ it from his mouth, ſave the laſt line: But ſaith, that perſon is now dead who gave him the ſaid Deſcription, but his wife is living.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sheridon</hi> being then called in and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, ſaid, He had no great acquaintance with the ſaid Doctor, and ſeldome ſaw him but upon a viſit, which happily might be once
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40664:4"/>a week or the like; Confeſſeth, That the ſaid Doctor told him as News, the Plot would now be laid open, for there was one ſent over into <hi>France</hi> to fetch a Prieſt that knew of the whole Plot: and further ſaith, That he that went over knew as much of the Plot as any man in <hi>England.</hi> Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Sheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Confeſſeth, That he went ſhortly after; but remembers not how long, to Secretary <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and told him that there was one gone over into <hi>France</hi> that knew as much of the Plot as any man, and that he went over to fetch a Prieſt that alſo knew the whole Plot, which he the ſaid <hi>Sheridon</hi> ſuppoſed was to be a Witneſs: Upon which the ſaid Secretary commanded him the ſaid <hi>Sheridon</hi> to give him a deſcription of the perſon ſo ſent over: but remembers no other diſcourſe at that time; But that ſome ſhort time after, but remembers not how long, he met with Mr. <hi>Day,</hi> who gave him the deſcription in the preſence of Mr. <hi>John Wilſon</hi> of the <hi>Middle Temple,</hi> which he ſhortly after delivered to the Secretary, and uſed as he remembers, only theſe words, Sir, Here is the deſcription of the perſon I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to you.</p>
            <p>After this Deſcription ſo delivered to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, a Letter was written by Mr. <hi>Cooke,</hi> (which Mr. <hi>Secretary</hi> declared at the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee he would take upon himſelf) in theſe words following,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:40664:5"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>White-Hall, <date>May 31. 1680.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <lb/>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Right Honourable Sir <hi>Leoline Jenkins,</hi> one of his Majeſties Principal Secretaries of State, being haſtily called this day to wait upon his Majeſty at <hi>Windſor,</hi> hath commanded me to ſend you the encloſed deſcription of a perſon, who, if he ſhall happen to come from <hi>France</hi> and land at your Port, Mr. Secretary ſaith, you will do the King and Kingdome a great ſervice if you will keep a ſtrict Eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and the company that ſhall arrive with him, till they be all brought before Mr. May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, or other chief Magiſtrate of your Town, whom Mr. Secretary deſires to offer the ſaid perſons the Oaths of Allegiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy; and in caſe of their or any of their refuſal of the ſame, to ſecure them and deal with them according to Law, giving Mr. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary an account with what ſpeed may be, of all the proceedings in this affair. If ſuch a perſon as is here deſcribed ſhould come and make no bones of taking the aforeſaid Oaths, yet in caſe Mr. Mayor or other chief Magiſtrate before whom they are brought, ſhall have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ground to ſuſpect that he is the man ſo deſcribed, and that he hath one or more in his company who may be reaſonably ſuſpected to be Prieſts, ſome handſome courſe is to be taken to detain them till Mr. Secretary can be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with what is done, and ſend ſuch further directions as ſhall be thought neceſſary. Mr. May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40664:5"/>authority, with your Prudence and Zeal in this matter, will I hope produce a good effect. Upon this Command I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your very Humble Servant, <hi>John Cooke.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Pray favour me with a Line that this comes ſafe to your hands.</p>
                     <closer/>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>Vera Copia.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>John Pepper.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </postscript>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which <hi>Norris</hi> was committed to the Common Priſon, as is mentioned in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. All which being of more than an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary nature, this Committee thought not fit to give any opinion, but humbly referred it to the Wiſdome of this Houſe.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
